<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A congratulation to France vpon the happy alliance with Spaine. Dedicated to the Queene. With the order and challenge of the knights of fame, to their opposites.</title>
            <author>Menantel, François de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102536</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838313</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838313</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1109:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A congratulation to France vpon the happy alliance with Spaine. Dedicated to the Queene. With the order and challenge of the knights of fame, to their opposites.</title>
                  <author>Menantel, François de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 2-15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Eld] for T. Thorp. and to be sold by W. Burre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Paris] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: F. de Menantel.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from colophon; printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut portrait on title page.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some pages stained, creased and torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIII, --  King of France, 1601-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2687:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2687:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONGRATVLATION TO FRANCE, VPON THE HAPPY ALLIANCE WITH
SPAINE.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to the Queene.</p>
            <p>With the order and challenge of the Knights of Fame, to their
oppoſites.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>LEWIS · THE XIII · KING OF FRANCE.</head>
               <figDesc>portrait of Louis XIII of France</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed for <hi>T. Thorp.</hi> and to be ſold by <hi>W.
Burre.</hi> 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2687:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2687:2"/>
            <head>To the Queene.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rance</hi> hath not without cauſe had recourſe to your
Maieſty as to her ſole remedy, and now Spaine intreats you to adorne her
Crowne with our <hi>Flower de Luces,</hi> for it ſeemeth that Heauen hath
made you the gardian of peace, and placed you in this world as the true Queene
vnto whome hee hath appointed the totall gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof; ſhewing vs
there by, that his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, that as one <hi>MARY</hi> brought peace into
the world, ſo your Maiesty ſhould distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to vs. For this cauſe
Madame, your <pb facs="tcp:2687:3"/>
Maieſty maybe pleaſed to giue me leaue to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame the glories
thereof, and ſing them on the Theater of my labours, that the whole world may
be acquainted with our happineſſe. My ſelfe being your Maiesties</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Moſt humble and obedient ſubiect and
ſeruant. F. de Menantel. S. Denis.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="congratulation">
            <pb facs="tcp:2687:3"/>
            <head>A Congratulation to France <hi>on the happy alliance</hi> with
Spaine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> I is not without cauſe, that thoſe Monarchies are held
happy, whoſe affections Heauen hath vnited: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the renewing of
Kings, God rewardeth his people accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the merit of their liues: for if
I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not, I haue read of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the tirant,
<hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> who imployed their power and
authority cruelly, and to the hurt of their people, which is an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2687:4"/>
ſigne, that God had forſaken them, by giuing them ſuch cruell
Princes. Our France is free from thoſe miſeries, and without bluſhing may
terme it ſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary happy, by hauing for a long time Kings ſacred
and choſen by that great God, who calls them his eldeſt and moſt
Chriſtian ſonnes: a matter which may ſtire vs vp to giue him thankes, and
to intreat him to continue this fauour, that wee may nouriſh our glory vnder
the wings of his almighty power. Doe we not owe him this acknowledgment, for
taking ſuch ſpeciall care of our peace? Let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the
greatneſſe of the preſent benifit hee hath beſtowed vpon vs, hauing
gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs a Queene, who is the pearle of the world, the ornament of Heauen, the
<hi>epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> of all vertues: For this, we ought to redouble our praiers,
and ſeeke hereafter better to pleaſe him, I meane by changing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2687:4"/>
our old conditions, and framing them a new in the model of his holy
commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: the which we may eaſily doe, our mindes being freed from the
rage of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition which poſſeſt vs when Spaine was an enemy to our
France: and now I doe aſſure my ſelfe our good <hi>Genius</hi> wil be
auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious, ſo long as hir Maieſty ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine among vs. What is
there more to be admired then our preſent gouernment? who would euer haue
thought that vpon the euen of warre, loſing our great <hi>Henry,</hi> we
ſhould haue enioyed ſuch tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? verily it is the worke of Heauen,
and we muſt of neceſſity ſo beleeue it, vnleſſe we thinke it to bee
our great <hi>Henries</hi> fame, which peraduenture hath left an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
terror behind him to awe other Kings, who being ſtill amazed at the report of
his vallour, haue not dared to make any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt vpon his lawfull heire, vnto
whom <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2687:5"/>
they feare he hath be queathed his courage as well as
greatneſſe: The which we ſhall vndoubtedly finde to be true by thoſe
liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignes which may be diſcerned in him. O hapyy day when her
Maieſty was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Regent. Bleſſed of God are you my Lords who gaue
your conſents; you may truly ſay that the holy Ghoſt ſpake in you at
that time when you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the States gouernment to her; Thereby you declare
that you worthily deſerue your places, &amp; that queſtionleſſe you had
a care of the publik peace. O let your ſacred Maieſties, who with a
liberall hand giues vs meanes to ſerue your greatneſſe, drawing your
poore France forth of the dangerous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice of warre, making it triumphant
on the worlds Theater; You I ſay who with your onely lookes braue the
greateſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Europe, preſerue and make much of your liues, that you
may eternize our <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2687:5"/>
peace, which can laſt no longer then you raigne in the world,
where al true French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men your humble ſeruants will beſeech the diuine
Maieſty that it may be ſo. For what greater fauours could wee hope for then
thoſe we now enioy? by what other way then this could her Maieſty haue
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured our good? There is none ſo ſimple but knowes that Spaine is more
then able to embroile our peace, and by conſequent her alliance moſt
profitable for France. Her Maieſty and my Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, whoſe
vnderſtanding pearceth Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, haue maturely diſpoſed of this
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and can make no appeale from this reſolution, beeing the
onely meanes to try our forces againſt the Turke and to reconquer that which
our vnbrideled am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition loſt do we not ſuppoſe but that this
conſideration did reunite the wandering affections of our Kings, who wearied
with <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2687:6"/>
ciuill diſſention haue reſolued vpon this deſeigne for when
did you euer reade that ciuill warre reigned ſo long among the Turkes, as it
hath done in Chriſtendome. Our Kings are children of a ſpirituall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
beleeue in him, liue vnder his law: what reaſon then haue weee to ſeeke and
deſire the ruyne, of our bretheren. Let vs imploy our courage in making warre
vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that tyrant, a ſworne enemy to our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and not make our
neighbours bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells ſcabbards for our ſwords; this will more renowne vs,
and our death will bee more glorious before God: the way is tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced before vs,
and an occaſion offered by the contracted marriages of our king with the
Infanta of Spaine, and is doubly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by that of the Princeſſe of
France, with the Prince of Spaine: all excuſes are vaine. O Lord thou art
mighty, thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is incomprehenſible and men can <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2687:6"/>
not ſound the depth of thy iudgements: wher is that dead
<hi>Chaos</hi> which we thought to haue beheld? wher are thoſe preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
which our <hi>Mars</hi> had leuied in France to glut our ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? O thou great
God haſt thou cauſed a ſecond <hi>MARY</hi> to be borne in the Eaſt?
Haſt thou ordained her from her birth to preuent our miſeries? I verily
thinke it, ſeeing that by her alone thou haſt freed vs from our long
troubles: Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh O good God, finiſh this worke, leaſt ſome wandring
fire fall into the trenches of our peace, and blow vp the myne of our hope,
which if it ſhould happen wee were then at the pitts brinke of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
miſeries: yet I doe not imagin that her Maieſty and our Princes would be
ſo merry and ioyfull as to proclaime tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes, if they were not aſſured
of our peace, and that thou hadeſt poſſeſt them with a deſire to
effect it. This O Lord <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2687:7"/>
we heartily beſeech thee to graunt, and we yeeld vnto thee the
ſame thankes which thy deere ſeruant <hi>Dauid</hi> did after that hee had
vanquiſhed his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and was peaceably ſeated in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="challenge">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2687:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE KNIGHTS OF</hi> Fames Challenge to all thoſe that
<hi>will oppoſe themſelues</hi> againſt them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>NDERSTAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the Oracles that the French <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi>
after his trauailes had builded the Pallace of Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that the
Deſtinies had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the firſt entrance into it for vs, and the proofe
of thoſe <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2687:8"/>
which deſerue the ſecond, to our Lances, we are come thither
vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the report of the Marriages of the greateſt Kings of Europe, to procure
witneſſes of our vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and to ſhew our ſelues Knights worthy of
imitation. For without looſing the title of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible, which our deeds haue
purchaſed, we will keepe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that Pallace againſt all men, and
maintaine</p>
            <p>That the beauty which wee reuerence is without compare, and her
actions blameleſſe.</p>
            <p>That they are ſo good as they can not be bettered.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2687:8"/>That we alone deſerue to
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh hir glory and that none ought to aſpire to ours.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe the fame of the aſſaillants ſhall not be
ſmall, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuch authors of their defeate be it that they come to vs as
wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with liuing in the world, or elſe deſirous to haue vs end their
daies, ſeeing that the honor to fight with vs is greater, then that of
vanquiſhing all other men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VVe <hi>Almidor, Leontides, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus, Liſander,
Arganto,</hi>
               </signed> will mayntaine this challenge in the <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2687:9"/>
place royall of Paris on the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fiue day of the Month of
<hi>MARS,</hi> who inſpire vs.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="decrees_of_the_lists">
            <head>
               <hi>THE DECREES OF</hi> the Liſts, and order of the courſes
<hi>at the Quintyn.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Defendants ſhal enter firſt into the place, and none
after them but thoſe that haue charge of the triumphes, aſſaillants, or
traine.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2687:9"/>2. The aſſailants
ſhall ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with viſards,
liueries, ſhields, names, armes of their houſes, and impreſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſhall enter the liſts at one of the clocke after
dinner, if they meane to runne, and ſhall cauſe a certaine number of
tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be brought thither.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They cannot enter the liſts without the leaue of the
Iudges of the field.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They ſhal runne according to he order as they entred,
and each of them onely with two <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2687:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ances.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He That breakes his lance from the chinne of the Quintin
to the eyes, wins one courſe, from thence vpward, two; in the ſmall
ſhield, three; in any other part nothing.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The lance ſhall not bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted broken vnles the
ſtaffe fall in two peeces.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Who loſeth his lance, ſword plume, bridle, ſpur, or
ſtirrop, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the courſe, and if he breakes not, wins nothing.</p>
            <p n="9">9. VVho loſeth his ſadle, or hits <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2687:10"/>
the great ſhield is to be thruſt forth of the liſts.</p>
            <p n="10">10. He that falls from his horſe incurs the like
penalty.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The value of the reward is at the choyſe of the
aſſaillants.</p>
            <p n="12">12. At their returne from the liſts, al of them ſhal
keepe the ſame order as they did at their entrance. The reſt is refered to
the Iudges.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Publiſhed at Paris the 13. day of the month of march. 1612.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
